<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd" [
<!ENTITY rfc2119 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2460 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2460.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2474 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2474.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc2702 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2702.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3031 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3031.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3168 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3168.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3209 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3209.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3270 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3270.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3550 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3550.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc3985 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3985.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4446 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4446.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4447 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4447.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc4448 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4448.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5086 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5086.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5087 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5087.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5129 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5129.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc5462 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5462.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6073 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6073.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6437 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6437.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6658 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6658.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6718 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6718.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc7167 PUBLIC "" "http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.7167.xml">
<!ENTITY rfc6733 PUBLIC ""
"http://xml2rfc.tools.ietf.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6733.xml">

<!ENTITY I-D.finn-detnet-problem-statement PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-finn-detnet-problem-statement-04.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.finn-detnet-architecture PUBLIC "" "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.draft-finn-detnet-architecture-02.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-isis-pcr SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-isis-pcr.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-6man-segment-routing-header SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-6man-segment-routing-header.xml">
<!ENTITY I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing.xml">

]>

<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc iprnotified="no"?>
<?rfc strict="yes"?>
<?rfc compact="yes"?>
<?rfc subcompact="yes"?>
<rfc category="info"
     docName="draft-dt-detnet-dp-alt-00"
	 ipr="trust200902"
	 submissionType="IETF">
  <front>
    <title abbrev="DetNet data plane alternatives">
     DetNet Data Plane Protocol and Solution Alternatives</title>

  <author role="editor" fullname="Jouni Korhonen" initials="J." surname="Korhonen">
   <organization abbrev="Broadcom">Broadcom</organization>
   <address>
    <postal>
     <street>3151 Zanker Road</street>
     <city>San Jose</city>
     <code>95134</code>
     <region>CA</region>
     <country>USA</country>
    </postal>
    <email>jouni.nospam@gmail.com</email>
   </address>
  </author>

  <author fullname="J&aacute;nos Farkas" initials="J." surname="Farkas">
   <organization abbrev="Ericsson">Ericsson</organization>
   <address>
    <postal>
     <street>Konyves K&aacute;lm&aacute;n krt. 11/B</street>
     <city>Budapest</city>
     <country>Hungary</country>
     <code>1097</code>
    </postal>
    <email>janos.farkas@ericsson.com</email>
   </address>
  </author>
  
  <author fullname="Norman Finn" initials="N." surname="Finn">
   <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco</organization>
   <address>
    <email>nfinn@cisco.com</email>
   </address>
  </author>
  
  <author fullname="Olivier Marce" initials="O." surname="Marce">
   <organization abbrev="Nokia Bell Labs">Nokia Bell Labs</organization>
   <address>
    <email>Olivier.Marce@nokia.com</email>
   </address>
  </author>
  
  <author fullname="Gregory Mirsky" initials="G." surname="Mirsky">
   <organization abbrev="Ericsson">Ericsson</organization>
   <address>
    <email>gregory.mirsky@ericsson.com</email>
   </address>
  </author>
  
  <author fullname="Pascal Thubert" initials="P." surname="Thubert">
   <organization abbrev="Cisco">Cisco</organization>
   <address>
    <email>pthubert@cisco.com</email>
   </address>
  </author>
  
  <author fullname="Zhuangyan Zhuang" initials="Z." surname="Zhuan">
   <organization abbrev="Huawei">Huawei</organization>
   <address>
    <email>zhuangyan.zhuang@huawei.com</email>
   </address>
  </author>
  
  <date />
  <workgroup>DetNet</workgroup>

  <abstract>
  <t>This document identifies existing IP and MPLS, and layer-2 encapsulations
   that run over IP and/or MPLS data plane technologies that could be considered
   as the base line solution alternatives for deterministic networking data plane
   definition.
  </t>
  </abstract>

  
  </front>

 <middle>
 <section title="Introduction">
  <t>
    Deterministic networking (DetNet) <xref
    target="I-D.finn-detnet-problem-statement"/> provides a capability to carry
    unicast or multicast data streams for real-time applications with extremely
    low data loss rates and known upper bound maximum latency <xref
    target="I-D.finn-detnet-architecture"/>. The deterministic networking
    Quality of Service (QoS) is expressed as 1) the minimum and maximum
    end-to-end latency from sender (talker) to receiver (listener), 2)
    probability of loss of a packet as a result of congestion, 3) probability
    of loss of a packet in the event of the failure of a relay system or link.
    Only the worst-case values for the mentioned parameters are concerned.
  </t>
  <t>There are three techniques to achieve the QoS required by deterministic networks:
   <list style="symbols">
    <t>zero congestion loss,</t>
    <t>explicit routes,</t>
    <t>packet replications and deletion.</t>
   </list>
   This document identifies existing IP and Multiprotocol Label Switching Architecture
   (MPLS) <xref target="RFC3031"/>, and layer-2 encapsulations
   that run over IP and/or MPLS data plane technologies that could be considered
   as the base line solution alternatives for deterministic networking data plane
   definition. The full scope of the deterministic networking data plane solution
   is considered including, as appropriate, quality of service (QoS), operations 
   and management (O&amp;M), and time synchronization.
  </t>
 </section>

 <!--section title="Terminology">
  <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
   "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
   document are to be interpreted as described in <xref
   target="RFC2119"></xref>.</t>
 </section-->


<section title="Criteria for data plane solution alternatives" anchor="sec_crit">
  <t>
   Each deterministic networking data plane solution alternative is described
   and evaluated using the criteria describe in this section. The used criteria
   enumerated in this section is selected so that it highlights the existence
   or lack of features that are expected or seen important to a solution
   alternative for the data plane solution. 
  </t>
 

  <section title="#1 Encapsulation and overhead" anchor="sec_crit_encap">
    <t>
     In several cases a deterministic flow/strem has to be encapsulated inside
     other protocols, for example, when transporting a layer-2 Ethernet
     frame over an IP transport network. In some cases a former tunneling like
     encapsulation can be avoided by underlying transport protocol translation,
     for example, translating layer-2 Ethernet frame including addressing and
     stream identification into native IP traffic. Last it is possible that
     talkers and listeners handle deterministic flows natively in a layer-3.
     This criteria concerns what is the encapsulation method the solution
     alternative support: tunneling like encapsulation, protocol translation or
     native layer-3 transport. In addition to the encapsulation mechanism this
     criteria is also concerned of the processing and specifically the 
     encapsulate header overhead.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section title="#2 Stream identification" anchor="sec_crit_streamid">
    <t>
     The solution alternative has to provide means to identify specific
     deterministic flows / streams. The stream identification can, for example,
     be explicit field in the data plane encapsulation header or implicitly
     encoded into the addressing scheme of the used data plane protocol. This
     criteria concerns the availability and details of deterministic flow /
     stream  identification the data plane protocol alternative has.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section title="#3 Packet sequencing" anchor="sec_crit_seq">
    <t>
     The solution alternative has to provide means for end systems to number
     packets sequentially and transport that sequencing information along with
     the sent packets. In addition to possible reordering packets one of the
     important uses for sequencing is detecting duplicates. In a case of
     intentional packet duplication a combination of stream identification and
     packet sequencing allows for detecting and discarding duplicates at the
     receiver (see <xref target="sec_crit_repdup"/> for more details).  This criteria
     concerns the availability and details of the packet sequencing
     capabilities the data plane protocol alternative has.
    </t>
  </section>
  
  
  <section title="#4 Explicit routes" anchor="sec_crit_explicit">
    <t>
     The solution alternative has to provide a mechanism(s) for establishing
     explicit routes that all packets belonging to a deterministic flow /
     stream will follow. The explicit route can be seen as a form of source
     routing or a pre-reserved path e.g., using some network management
     procedure. It should be noted that the explicit route does not need to be
     detailed to a level where every possible intermediate node along the path
     is part of the named explicit route. The IEEE 802.1Qca <xref
     target="IEEE8021Qca"/> specification defines how to do explicit path
     control in a bridged network and its IETF counter part is defined in 
     <xref target="I-D.ietf-isis-pcr"/>. This criteria concerns the
     available mechanisms for explicit routes for the data plane protocol
     alternative.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section title="#5 Packet replication and deletion" anchor="sec_crit_repdup">
    <t>
     End systems and/or relay systems can number packets sequentially,
     replicate them, and later eliminate all but one of the replicas, at
     multiple points in the network in order to ensure that one (or more)
     equipment failure events still leave at least one path intact for a
     deterministic networking stream. The goal is to enable seamless
     "protection switching" in a way that no packet gets lost or there is
     no ramp up time when either one of the paths fails for one reason or
     another.
    </t>
    <t>
     The IEEE 802.1CB <xref target="IEEE8021CB"/> is an example of
     Ethernet-based solution that defines packet sequence numbering, packet
     replication, and duplicate packet identification and deletion. The
     deterministic networking data plane solution alternative at layer-3 has to
     provide equivalent functionality. This criteria concerns the available
     mechanisms for packet replication and duplicate deletion the data plane
     protocol alternative has.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section title="#6 Operations and management" anchor="sec_crit_oam" >
    <t>
     The solution alternative should demonstrate an availability of appropriate
     standardized O&amp;M tools or control/management plane that can be
     extended for deterministic networking purposes with a reasonable effort,
     when required. The O&amp;M tools do not necessarily need to be specific to
     the data plane protocol as it could be the case, for example, with
     MPLS-based data planes.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section title="#7 Time synchronization" anchor="sec_crit_sync">
    <t>
     The solution alternative may benefit from having a sense of time or at
     least that the associated O&amp;M protocols had time synchronization
     properties. One concrete example is Realtime Transport Protocol (RTP)
     <xref target="RFC3550"/>, which carries timestamps in the protocol header
     in addition to sequence numbers, has a  well specified algorithms, for
     example, for jitter calculations, and also has an associated control
     channel, the Realtime Transport Control Protocol (RTCP). Another example
     could be residence time measurement support for MPLS network domain using
     Generic Associated Channel (G-ACh) extensions. This criteria concerns the
     available mechanisms for time synchronization in the context of the
     data plane protocol alternative.
    </t>
  </section>

  <section title="#8 Class and quality of service capabilities" anchor="sec_crit_qos">
    <t>
     The data plane solution alternative should provide means for class of
     service (Cos) based traffic classification, for example, for queuing
     discipline.  Existing CoS traffic classification enablers include but are
     not limited to IP header differentiated services code point (DSCP) field
     <xref target="RFC2474"/>, MPLS label traffic class field <xref
     target="RFC5462"/>, and IEEE 803.1p priority code point (PCP) field to name
     few.
    </t>
    <t>
     Quality of Service (QoS) is a mechanism for flow/stream specific traffic
     treatment and include a quarantee/agreement for the service.  In the
     context of the data plane solution alternative there should be means for
     flow/stream identification, which then can be used to map a flow/stream
     against specific resources and and treatment in a node enforcing the QoS.
    </t>
    <t> 
     This Criteria concerns the availability and mechanisms for the CoS and QoS
     marking and signaling as a part of the data plane protocol solution alternative.
    </t>
  </section>
  <section title="#9 Packet traceability" anchor="sec_crit_trace">
    <t>
     For the network management and specifically for tracing down
     implementation or network configuration errors any means to find out
     whether a packet is a replica, which node performed replication, and
     which path was intended for the replica, can be very useful.
     This criteria concerns the availability of solutions for
     tracing packets in the context of data plane protocol alternative.
    </t>
  </section>
  <section title="#10 Technical maturity" anchor="sec_crit_matu">
    <t>
     The technical maturity of the data plane solution alternative is crucial,
     since it  basically defines the effort, time line and risks involved for
     the use of the solution in deployments. For example, the maturity level
     can be categorised as available immediately, available with small
     extensions, available with repurposing/redefining portions of the protocol
     or its header fields.  Yet another important measure for maturity is the
     deployment experience. This criteria concerns the maturity of the data
     plane protocol alternative as the solution alternative.
    </t>
  </section>
</section>


<section title="Data plane solution alternatives">
 <t>
  The following sections describe and rate deterministic data plane solution
  alternatives. In "Analysis and Discussion" section each alternative is
  evaluated against the criteria given in <xref target="sec_crit"/> and rated
  using the following: (M)eets the criteria, (W)ork needed, and (N)ot suitable
  or too much work envisioned.
 </t>

 <section title="Native IPv4 transport" anchor="sec_alt_ipv4">
  <section title="Solution description">
  </section>

  <section title="Analysis and Discussion">
  </section>

  <section title="Summary">
  </section>
 </section>

 <section title="Native IPv6 transport" anchor="sec_alt_ipv6">

  
  <section title="Solution description">
   <t>
    This section investigates the application of native IPv6 <xref
    target="RFC2460"/> as the data plane for DetNet along the criteria
    collected in <xref target="sec_crit"/>.
   </t>
  </section>
  
  <section title="Analysis and Discussion">
   <t><list style="hanging">
    <t hangText="Encapsulation and overhead (W)">
     <vspace blankLines="1"/>
     Deterministic flows are assumed to be handled natively at layer-3 by IPv6
     at the first place. The fixed header of an IPv6 packet is 40 bytes <xref
     target="RFC2460"/>.  The overhead is bigger if any extension header is
     used. However, the exact overhead (<xref target="sec_crit_encap"/>)
     depends on what solution is actually used to provide DetNet features,
     e.g., explicit routing or seamless redundancy if any of these is applied.
     <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
    
    <t hangText="Stream identification (M/W)">
     <vspace blankLines="1"/>
     The 20-bit flow label field of the fixed IPv6 header is suitable to
     distinguish different deterministic flows/streams. But guidance on the use
     of the flow label provided by <xref target="RFC6437"/> places restrictions
     on how the flow label can be used. In particular, labels should be chosen
     from an approximation to a discrete uniform distribution. Additionally,
     existing implementations generally do not open APIs to control the flow
     label from the upper layers.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
    
    <t hangText="Packet sequencing (W/N)">
     <vspace blankLines="1"/>
     TBD. [Editor's note: packet sequencing would require a new extension
     header - a destination option most likely - to add sequence numbers.]
    <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
    
    <t hangText="Explicit routes (W)">
     <vspace blankLines="1"/>
     There is an initiative to equip IPv6 with explicit routing capabilities.
     The idea is to apply Segment Routing (SR) <xref
     target="I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing"/> to IPv6 via the addition of a
     new type of routing extension header <xref
     target="I-D.ietf-6man-segment-routing-header"/>.  
    <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
    
    <t hangText="Packet replication and deletion (W)">
     <vspace blankLines="1"/>
     The implementation of this functionality largely depends on the packet
     sequencing and flow/stream identification approaches used. Specifically in
     a case of packet replication the replicated packets are likely to be
     sourced from a different IPv6 address than the original packets, thus the
     flow/stream identification that is independent of the addressing becomes
     important. At present sequencing and flow/stream identification beyond IPv6
     flow label would require new IPv6 extension headers. Also, there is no
     specification for the duplicate packet deletion functionality at merging
     points.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
    
    <t hangText="Operations and management (M/W)">
     <vspace blankLines="1"/>
     IPv6 enjoys the existing toolbox for generic IP network management.
     However, IPv6 specific management features are still not at the level of
     that IPv4 has. This specifically concerns the areas that are IPv6 specific,
     for example, related to neighbor discovery protocol (ND), stateless address
     autoconfiguration (SLAAC), subscriber identification, and security.
     While the standards are already mostly in place the implementations in
     deployed equipment can be lacking or inadequate for commercial
     deployments. This is largely only an issue with old existing equipment.
   <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
    
    <t hangText="Time synchronization (W/N)">
     <vspace blankLines="1"/>
     IPv6 has no existing supporting mechanisms for anything time
     synchronization. A new extension header would be needed for this purpose,
     if such functionality is required.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
    
    <t hangText="Class and quality of service capabilities (M)">
     <vspace blankLines="1"/>
     The traffic class field of the fixed IPv6 header is designed for this purpose.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
    
    <t hangText="Packet traceability (M/W/N)">
     <vspace blankLines="1"/>
     The traceability of replicated packets also depends on the sequencing
     mechanism. As noted earlier, there is no header field whose application
     would be straightforward as a field for packet sequencing.  Furthermore,
     traceability would need a mechanism to trace back the reverse route the
     packet took in some cases. While IPv6 as such has no support for this, it
     appears source route extensions such as the one defined for segment routing
     could be used for tracing purposes.
     <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
    
    <t hangText="Technical maturity (M/W)">
     <vspace blankLines="1"/>
     IPv6 has been around about 20 years. However, large scale global and
     commercial IPv6 deployments are rather new dating only few years back to
     around 2012. While IPv6 has proven itself there are number of small issues
     to work on as they show up once operations experience grows. A good meter
     is the number of basic IPv6 related documents in IETF V6OPS, V6MAN and
     other use case specific working groups.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
   </list></t>
  </section>

  <section title="Summary">
   <t>
    TBD.
   </t>
  </section>
 </section>

 <section title="Layer-2 tunneling over IP">
  <section title="GRE" anchor="sec_alt_gre">
   <section title="Solution description">
   </section>

   <section title="Analysis and Discussion">
   </section>

   <section title="Summary">
   </section>
  </section>
    
  <section title="L2TP" anchor="sec_alt_l2tp">
   <section title="Solution description">
   </section>

   <section title="Analysis and Discussion">
   </section>

   <section title="Summary">
   </section>
  </section>

 </section>
  
 <section title="IP/MPLS">
  <section title="Solution description">
  </section>

  <section title="Analysis and Discussion">
  </section>

  <section title="Summary">
  </section>
 </section>
  
 <section title="PseudoWires" anchor="sec_alt_pwe">
  <section title="Solution description">
   <t>
    PSeudo Wire Emulation (PWE)  <xref target="RFC3985"/> or PseudoWires (PW)
    provide means of emulating the essential attributes and behaviour of a
    telecommunications service over a packet switched network (PSN) using IP or
    MPLS transport.  In addition to traditional telecommunications services
    such as T1 line or Frame Relay, PWs also provide transport for Ethernet
    service <xref target="RFC4448"/> and for generic packet service <xref
    target="RFC6658"/>.
   </t>
   <t>
    PWs appear as a good data plane solution alternative for a number of
    reasons. PWs are a proven and deployed technology with a rich O&amp;M
    control plane <xref target="RFC4447"/>, and enjoy the toolbox developed for
    MPLS networks. Furthermore, PWs may have an optional Control Word (CW) as
    part of the payload encapsulation between the PSN and the emulated service
    that is, for example, capable of frame sequencing and duplicate detection.
    The encapsulation layer may also provide timing  <xref target="RFC5087"/>.
   </t>
  </section>

  <section title="Analysis and Discussion">
   <t><list style="hanging">
    <t hangText="Encapsulation and overhead (M)">
     <vspace blankLines="1"/>
     PWs offer encapsulation services practically for any types of payloads
     over any PSN.  New PW types need a code point allocation <xref
     target="RFC4446"/> and in some cases an emulated service specific
     document.
     <vspace blankLines="1"/>
     Specifically in the case of the MPLS PSN the PW encapsulation overhead is
     minimal. Typically minimum two labels and a CW is needed, which totals to
     12 octets. PW type specific handling might, however, allow optimizations
     on the emulated service in the provider edge (PE) device's native service
     processing (NSP) / forwarder function. These optimizations could be used,
     for example, to reduce header overhead.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
    
    <t hangText="Stream identification (M)">
     <vspace blankLines="1"/>
     PWs provide multiple layers of stream identification, especially in the case
     of the MPLS PSN. The PWs are typically prepended with a PW label that can be
     used to identify a specific PW. Furthermore, the PSN also uses one or more
     labels to transport packets over a specific label switched paths (that then'
     would carry PWs).
    <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
    
    <t hangText="Packet sequencing (M)">
     <vspace blankLines="1"/>
     As mentioned earlier PWs may contain an optional CW that is able to provide
     sequencing services. The size of the sequence number in the generic CW is
     16 bits, which might be, depending on the used link speed be too little.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
    
    <t hangText="Explicit routes (M)">
     <vspace blankLines="1"/>
     In a case of the MPLS PSN the traffic engineering toolbox developed for
     MPLS can be used to signal explicit label switched paths (LSP) <xref
     target="RFC2702"/><xref target="RFC3209"/>.  Furthermore, the PSN may also
     use segment routing (SR) to provide explicit routes <xref
     target="I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing"/> <xref
     target="I-D.ietf-6man-segment-routing-header"/>.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
    
    <t hangText="Packet replication and deletion (W)">
     <vspace blankLines="1"/>
     The 1+1 PW/LSP protection / redundancy mechanisms  <xref
     target="RFC6718"/> could provide tools for packet replication. However,
     these solutions are not really intended for sourcing multiple simultaneous
     packet streams. The solutions have one active and other standby stream.
     The PW duplicate detection mechanism also exists in theory <xref
     target="RFC3985"/> but no emulated service makes use of it currently.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
    
    <t hangText="Operations and management (M/W)">
     <vspace blankLines="1"/>
     PWs have rich control plane for O&amp; and in a case of the MPLS PSN enjoy
     the full control plane toolbox developed for MPLS network O&amp;M. There
     could be, however, need for deterministic networking specific extensions
     for the mentioned control planes.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
    
    <t hangText="Time synchronization (M)">
     <vspace blankLines="1"/>
     It is possible to carry time synchronization information as part of the PW
     encapsulation layer (see for example <xref target="RFC5087"/>). Whether
     the timing precision is enough for all deterministic networking use cases
     vary, and it is possible existing mechanisms are not adequate for all use
     cases.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
    
    <t hangText="Class and quality of service capabilities (M)">
     <vspace blankLines="1"/>
     In a case of IP PSN the 6-bit differentiated services code point (DSCP)
     field can be used for indicating the class of service <xref
     target="RFC2474"/> and 2-bit field reserved fir the explicit congestion
     notification (ECN) <xref target="RFC3168"/>. Similarly, in a case of MPLS
     PSN, there are 3-bit traffic class field (TC) <xref target="RFC5462"/> in
     the label reserved for for both  Explicitly TC-encoded-PSC LSPs (E-LSP)
     <xref target="RFC3270"/> and ECN <xref target="RFC5129"/>.  Due to the
     limited number of bits in the TC field, their use for QoS and ECN
     functions restricted and intended to be flexible. Although the Qos/CoS
     mechanism is already in place some clarifications may be required in the
     context of deterministic networking flows/streams, for example, if some
     specific mapping between bit fields have to be done.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
    
    <t hangText="Packet traceability (M/W)">
     <vspace blankLines="1"/>
     In a case of MPLS PSN and an approach where PWs are prepended with a PSN
     layer outer label (or more labels in a stack) help tracing the explicit
     reverse path of the packet using the outer label(s) as the key. Even if the
     PW labels of the duplicated packets were the same the outer labels should
     be different. However, even this approach is not "perfect" since the
     intermediate node identities are not recorded into the packet hop-by-hop
     basis as some protocol do (for example, Diameter protocol loop detection
     <xref target="RFC6733"/>).
    <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
    
    <t hangText="Technical maturity (M)">
     <vspace blankLines="1"/>
     PWs and MPLS are both proved technologies with wide variety of deployments
     and years of operational experience. Furthermore, the estimated work for
     missing functionality (packet replication and deletion) does not appear to
     be extensive, since the existing protection mechanism already get close to
     what is needed from the deterministic networking data plane solution.
    <vspace blankLines="1"/></t>
   </list></t>
  </section>

  <section title="Summary">
   <t>
    PseudoWires appear to be a strong candidate as the deterministic networking
    data plane solution alternative. The strong points are the technical maturity
    and the extensive control plane for O&amp;M. This holds specifically for 
    MPLS-based PSN.
   </t>
   <t>
    Extensions are required to realize the packet replication and duplicate detection.
    feature of the deterministic networking data plane.
   </t>
  </section>
 </section>

 <section title="Bit Indexed Explicit Replication" anchor="sec_alt_bier">
  <t>
   *Greg to write the initial text*
  </t>
  <section title="Solution description">
  </section>

  <section title="Analysis and Discussion">
  </section>

  <section title="Summary">
  </section>
 </section>


</section>

<section title="Summary of data plane alternatives">
  <t>TBD. A condenced summary of all solution alternative.
  </t>
   
  <texttable anchor="tab_all_summary" title="PseudoWire criteria summary">
   <ttcol align="left">Alternative</ttcol>
   <ttcol align="left">Comments</ttcol>
   <c>Native IPv4</c>
   <c>..</c>
   <c>Native IPv6</c>
   <c>..</c>
   <c>GRE</c>
   <c>..</c>
   <c>L2TP</c>
   <c>..</c>
   <c>IP/MPLS</c>
   <c>..</c>
   <c>PWE</c>
   <c>..</c>
   <c>BIER</c>
   <c>..</c>
  </texttable>
</section>


<section title="Security considerations">
  <t>TBD. Analysis per solution alternative.
  </t>
</section>


<section anchor="iana" title="IANA Considerations">
  <t>This document has no IANA considerations.
  </t>
</section>

<section anchor="acks" title="Acknowledgements">
  <t>The author(s) ACK and NACK.
  </t>
</section>
</middle>

<back>
  <references title="Normative References">
   &rfc2119;
  </references>
  <references title="Informative References">
   &rfc2460;
   &rfc3031;
   &rfc3985;
   &rfc3550;
   
   &rfc2474;
   &rfc2702;
   &rfc3168;
   &rfc3209;
   &rfc3270;
   &rfc4446;
   &rfc4447;
   &rfc4448;
   &rfc5087;
   &rfc5129;
   &rfc5462;
   &rfc6658;
   &rfc6073;
   &rfc6437;
   &rfc6718;
   &rfc7167;
   &rfc6733;
   &I-D.finn-detnet-problem-statement;
   &I-D.finn-detnet-architecture;
   &I-D.ietf-isis-pcr;
   &I-D.ietf-spring-segment-routing;
   &I-D.ietf-6man-segment-routing-header;

      <reference anchor="TSNTG"
       target="http://www.IEEE802.org/1/pages/avbridges.html">
        <front>
          <title>IEEE 802.1 Time-Sensitive Networks Task Group</title>
          <author>
            <organization>IEEE Standards Association</organization>
          </author>
          <date year="2013" />
        </front>
      </reference>
  
   <reference anchor="IEEE8021CB"
     target="http://www.ieee802.org/1/files/private/cb-drafts/d2/802-1CB-d2-1.pdf">
    <front>
     <title>Draft Standard for Local and metropolitan area networks - Seamless Redundancy</title>
     <author initials="N. F." surname="Finn" fullname="Norman Finn">
      <organization>IEEE 802.1</organization>
     </author>
     <date month="December" year="2015"/>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name="IEEE P802.1CB /D2.1" value="P802.1CB"/>
    <format type="PDF" target="http://www.ieee802.org/1/files/private/cb-drafts/d2/802-1CB-d2-1.pdf"/>
   </reference>

   <reference anchor="IEEE8021Qca"
     target="http://www.ieee802.org/1/files/private/ca-drafts/d2/802-1Qca-d2-1.pdf">
    <front>
     <title>IEEE 802.1Qca Bridges and Bridged Networks - Amendment: Path Control and Reservation</title>
     <author>
      <organization>IEEE 802.1</organization>
     </author>
     <date month="June" year="2015"/>
    </front>
    <seriesInfo name="IEEE P802.1Qca/D2.1" value="P802.1Qca"/>
    <format type="PDF" target="http://www.ieee802.org/1/files/private/ca-drafts/d2/802-1Qca-d2-1.pdf"/>
   </reference>
  
  
  </references>
 </back>
</rfc>

